Previously on "Castle"...
Who killed my mother?
No, Kate. I give you a name, I know you.
You'll run straight at him.
I might as well shoot you where you stand.
They are coming to kill you,
and I'm not gonna let 'em.
I'm gonna end this.
No one outside of this immediate family
ever needs to know about this.
As far as the world is concerned,
Roy Montgomery died a hero.
Kate!
It was supposed to be over.
Montgomery sacrificed
himself to keep her safe.
This is so much bigger than you realize.
Hello.
Mr. Castle,
I'm a friend of Roy Montgomery's.
We need to talk.
He says she's safe now on one condition.
She can't go near her mother's case.
She'll listen to me. I can steer her away.
No! Ah!
Beckett!
Castle!
Castle, I'm here!
Beckett, hang on!
Either this is the most
boring dream I've ever had
or you can't sleep either.
It's not a dream. More like a nightmare.
Is this about your valedictorian speech?
It's my chance to say something important,
something worthy.
I don't want to blow it, but I
feel like I have nothing to say.
You mean nothing compared to
the great sacred texts of mankind
or Winston Churchill's speech to harrows,
or Steve Jobs' address to Stanford?
You know, maybe you
should pick some speeches
st a little less daunting
to compare yours to,
like, um, "Say Anything" or "Twilight."
It's not supposed to be this hard.
You know, the most
worthwhile things in life
are often the most difficult.
For example--
Wow. That really is a smart phone.
Of course you don't understand
why she's taking her graduation
speech so seriously.
You were probably the guy who
had nothing on but boxers
underneath his gown.
That is so insulting.
If you must know, I was naked underneath.
Oh, I'm sorry. I stand corrected.
So how is the father of
the graduate taking it?
I already have a plan to drown my sorrows.
After the ceremony, my mother
goes off to the Hamptons,
Alexis will be doing her all-nighter.
I will be distracting myself
with a double feature
of "The Killer" and "Hard Boiled."
Wow. That is a double feature.
You like John Woo?
The bloodier the better.
You wouldn't want to... join me, would you?
Actually, I'd love to.
You coming, Castle?
Yeah. Please.
Hey.
So?
So we've got a Hispanic male, late 20s.
Cabbie spotted the body about an hour ago
and called it in.
We got an I.D.?
Nah. We checked his pockets.
There's no phone, keys, or wallet.
And we're checking prints right now.
From the blood trail, it
looks like he was shot
before he entered the alley.
He was hit in the shoulder
with what looks like a .357,
but the kill shot--
point-blank, execution style,
with a 9 millimeter.
Two guns. Could be more than one shooter.
Was C.S.U. able to trace that blood trail
from the first shot?
It starts around the corner.
There's no visible point of origin,
but the teams are still looking.
Well, this is a bad neighborhood.
Maybe it was a mugging gone wrong?
Maybe.
These grooves in his shoulder indicate
that he was carrying
something, and it was heavy.
I'd say at least 30 pounds.
I'm even seeing traces of skin
tissue in his fingernail.
I may be able to get D.N.A.,
but I'll know a lot more once
I get him back to the morgue.
Uh, his pockets may have been empty,
but it looks like he was trying
to hide something in his shoe.
Lock picks?
Now why would someone
be needing lock picks?
He's a thief.
Orlando Costas.
A couple of domestic B&Es, but
suspected of a dozen more.
He used to run with the Cazadores.
Cazadores?
They're a violent street
gang that deals in drugs,
arms, and larceny,
but all of Orlando's priors are
back when he was a teenager.
He hasn't been arrested in years.
Maybe he got back in the game.
I don't know. He went a long
way to clean up his act.
Did four years active in the military,
discharged with honors last year.
Spent his rotation as an M.P. in Germany.
Military police? He really
did clean up his act.
If this guy went straight,
then how did he end up dead in an alley?
Did you check for next of kin?
Uh, his folks are dead,
but we managed to track down a
girlfriend--Marisol Castaneda.
Esposito's bringing her in right now.
All I know is, he was
with me in bed last night
when I went to sleep.
I woke up this morning,
and both him and my car were gone.
Where did he go?
I figured he'd gone to the career center
to check the job listings.
He does that every morning.
He'd been looking for work?
For months.
Orlando served his country.
You'd think that means something,
but it's been tough,
especially after my hours got cut.
So he was under financial pressure?
Is it possible that he
went back to old habits?
No.
Look, Marisol, we know that
he ran with the Cazadores.
Do you think that--
I said no.
He went through hell to escape that life.
It's why he enlisted, to get out,
to be a better man for me...
A better father to our son.
So how about you stop trying
to make this his fault
and find whoever killed him?
What kind of car do you have?
Two blocks away from the alley,
blood smeared on the arm rest--
This is definitely it.
He was shot somewhere else
and then he came here?
Why not go home? Why not go get patched up?
He was meeting someone in that alleyway.
Phone.
His last call was 4:47 A.M.,
just before he died.
Run that number.
Right.
Hey, Beckett, gun.
It's a .38.
Recently fired.
So it was a shootout.
That's how he got the shoulder wound.
Which means,
wherever he came from, there
might be another body.
I know where he was coming from.
Where?
His last entry was 299 First Avenue.
Wait. What's at 299 First Ave.?
Captain Montgomery's house.
We're just thankful no one was hurt.
Believe me, so am I.
Ever since Roy died,
I've slept with his .357 in the nightstand.
So it was just the one guy?
As far as I know.
He was taking files out of the cabinet.
He had Roy's old laptop in his backpack.
When he saw me, he pulled his weapon,
so God help me, I shot him.
I think I hit him in his shoulder.
He fired back, and then he
crashed through the window.
Evelyn, was this the guy?
Yeah. That's him.
I'm glad Evan and the girls weren't home.
Funny thing is,
I wasn't supposed to be home either.
It's almost like he knew we
weren't supposed to be here.
Anything special about those files?
Just paperwork, legal documents,
notes on Roy's old cases.
What about his computer?
What--what was on that?
His old work files, but mostly,
I use it for Christmas cards and recipes.
They went after Montgomery's files.
Not valuables, not cash.
And now our thief is dead
and the files he took are missing?
Well, let's not jump to conclusions.
What else would it be about?
Everyone here thinks Montgomery died
bringing a cop killer to justice.
We're the only ones who know
what he was really involved in
and his connection to your mother's murder.
Beckett, it can't be a coincidence.
Recheck the vic's rap sheet.
See if Montgomery was involved
in any of his old arrests,
and get on that number.
I want to know who he was
talking to just before he died.
Say something reassuring.
There are thousands of break-ins
in New York City every year.
This one feels different.
Well, that doesn't mean that it is.
Montgomery worked hundreds of cases.
Just because this guy was after files
doesn't mean he was after your mom's case.
Then why is our thief dead?
You know those people that
Montgomery was involved with,
he said that they wanted me dead,
that I was getting too close,
and he said that he was gonna give his life
in order to protect mine,
and they still tried to kill me.
I wake up sometimes, and I think to myself,
how the hell am I still alive?
It's like I'm just waiting
for that other shoe to drop.
What if this is that other shoe?
Sync by YYeTs
Corrections by honeybunny
www.addic7ed.com
Things were finally getting better for her,
for us.
She was just coming out of her shell,
and now this?
Do you really think it's related
to her mother's murder case?
I hope to God it isn't.
Montgomery's friend was very clear.
She starts poking around
her mother's murder,
they'll come after her again.
I can't let that happen.
I know.
Thank you.
Did you get any sleep?
Not much.
Anything new on our victim?
We rechecked Orlando's rap sheet.
Montgomery wasn't involved
in any of his old arrests.
That break-in wasn't personal.
What about the call he
made before he was killed?
It's from a burner phone.
There's no registered owner.
Hey.
Hmm?
You're not in this alone.
I'm here.
I know.
Hey.
We may have been wrong
about why they hit Montgomery's.
Witnesses saw a Hispanic
male fleeing the alley
in a late-model Maroon DeVille.
Apparently he had gang ink on his neck--
a lion framed by a "C."
Cazador?
The very same gang that
our victim ran with.
Gangs.
If this guy was in that alley,
odds are, he killed Orlando.
Did we get a license plate?
Uh, no, but according to gang task force,
the ride matches the car
of one Vicente Delgado.
High-level shot caller for the Cazadores.
And get this.
His cousin Diego Gutierrez
was busted by Montgomery
for a double homicide in '95.
His lawyer's filed a motion for retrial
a month after Montgomery was killed.
Find him.
NYPD! Let me see your hands right now!
Don't move! Don't move! Don't move!
Let me see your hands!
Well, looky here,
a 9 millimeter.
Just like the gun that
killed Orlando Costas.
I already told you, I was
nowhere near that alley.
Fact is, your witnesses are blind.
The fact is, you knew Orlando Costas.
Yeah, I knew him once,
before he turned his back.
When was the last time you heard from him?
Not in years.
Hours.
Just before he was killed,
Orlando called a burner cell,
same phone that we found on you.
So why don't you just admit to
it and save yourself 30 years?
You had him break in to
Roy Montgomery's house
and steal your cousin's case files,
and then you shot him.
What you got, chica, huh?
Gun's not gonna be a match.
So that leaves you with what, a phone call,
and a couple of people who
saw a very common car?
You know why you can't
pin this on me, chica?
I wasn't there.
The hell you weren't.
That's gonna be ballistics.
Last chance to make a deal.
Book him on the drugs and weapons charge
and tell the D.A. I'm gonna
want to file for murder one.
It wasn't him.
What do you mean, it wasn't him?
The skin tissue that
Lanie was able to scrape
from underneath our victim's fingernails,
the lab was able to pull D.N.A.
We ran it against Vicente.
It's not a match.
In fact, it wasn't a match
to anyone in the system.
But it did match D.N.A. trace evidence
found at another crime scene.
Well, at least that's something.
What was the crime scene?
It was a shooting.
Beckett, it was your shooting.
D.N.A. confirms that the man
who killed Orlando Costas in that alley
is the same man who put
a bullet in your heart.
No leads for 11 months, and now this.
Does Gates know?
No.
Then we don't tell her.
If she finds out this is
a match to my shooting,
she'll take me off the case.
Maybe you should be off this case.
They tried to kill you once, Kate.
You keep going on this, they...
What's to stop them from trying again?
What's to stop them now?
No.
I've been waiting a year for this,
and I'll be damned if I let
someone else screw it up.
Hey, Javier.
Man, this just feels wrong.
We need to tell Gates.
Why...
So she can send Beckett home?
You think that's gonna work?
You think that's gonna stop her?
She's gonna investigate this case, Kevin,
whether she's on it or not.
The least we can do
is make sure that we have her back.
Hello.
I think you know why I'm
calling, Mr. Castle.
It's you.
Thank God. What the hell is going on?
Why'd they break in to Montgomery's place?
Well, most likely, it's a clean-up job.
Making sure that Montgomery had
nothing else incriminating
in his files.
As long as Beckett drops her investigation,
we still hold all the cards.
No, she's already on to her shooter.
She's not gonna let go.
Then we have a problem.
If she doesn't stop, they will retaliate.
Now I can't control the situation
if you can't control her.
I got enough on the drug
and weapons charges
to put you away for at least five years.
Five years of your life...
What's that worth?
I know you didn't kill Orlando.
But he called you,
and you talked to him for two minutes,
and you were in that alley.
Why?
There's nobody in here but you and me.
There's no cameras,
no microphones, no one's listening.
I can make all those charges go away.
Five years of your life back,
but you gotta tell me what you know.
He called last week.
Talking about "Times were bad,"
so I told him, "I can get you some work."
But he knew if he came
back to the Cazadores,
there'd be no leaving this time.
And all he really wanted was a loan
and could I help him out
for old times' sake.
Did you give it to him?
No. He begged me.
Said he was good for it.
Said he had something big coming up,
something that'd make him whole.
Did he say what?
No, but that morning, my phone rings,
and he said it'd all gone wrong,
he was desperate, talking about
they were gonna kill him.
Who's they?
Don't know.
But he was scared.
Why did he call you?
Protection, chica.
He said if I helped him
out, he'd come back,
and he knew that was the price.
So I told him where to meet.
But by the time I got
there, he was already dead.
You told him where to meet?
That's right.
You didn't tell anyone else?
No.
Did you see anything there?
White guy,
6'.
Caught a glimpse before the
night swallowed him whole.
They must have been
tapping Orlando's phone.
That's the only way they got there first.
But how did they know to
target Orlando for the job?
Because he was desperate for money.
Yeah, but how did they know that?
How did they know his background?
Because they knew him from the military.
He was hired by somebody he knew.
It's a place to start.
And whoever's gotten close
to that secret is dead.
I think it's clear, we're
in over our heads here.
Speak for yourself, bro.
Orlando's financials just came in.
He was underwater and
overdrawn until last week
when a wire transfer for
10 grand hit his account.
Let me guess. Untraceable?
So it's a dead end.
The deposits are,
but the debit withdrawals are not.
Right when the money came in,
Marisol started using it to pay bills.
Wait. If Marisol knew about the money...
Then she knew Orlando was up to something.
She lied to us.
Not only that, but according to the bank,
she cleaned out the entire
account an hour ago.
She's on the run.
I've got a few questions for
you before you leave town,
and this time,
I want the truth.
I'm telling you the truth.
I didn't know anything about the money.
Not until today.
So why do we have debits against it
the moment it appeared in your account?
Orlando--
It was your card, Marisol.
Who was Orlando working for?
Do you know what's gonna happen
if you don't cooperate?
You're gonna go to jail
and your kid's gonna go to foster care.
Is that what you want?
Beckett--
Marco on the streets,
enlisted by the Cazadores
at age 10 like his father,
dead in a gutter at 19!
Pudrete en el infierno!
Beckett...
That's enough.
Orlando said it was someone
he knew from the service,
someone dangerous.
But it was just a one-off,
a lot of money for an easy job.
And we needed the money.
What was the job?
They needed files...
from a dead cop's house.
What files?
All of them, any he could find,
this guy from the service,
did you get a name?
No.
Did you meet him?
Did he ever call the house?
He left notes for Orlando in the mail box
with a time and place.
They were coded so I-I wouldn't know where.
But I was in the car once.
I saw where they met.
At a church
over on State Street.
Wednesday, you say?
Yeah, around 3:00 P.M.
He was meeting with someone.
I'm sorry. I wish I could help.
But we're open to the public,
and we get a lot of
unfamiliar faces every day.
We usually just leave
them to their prayers.
If your donation box is any indication,
it looks like being open to the
public comes with a price.
Yes, well... it's not
the best neighborhood.
We catch gang kids and the
homeless all the time,
trying to take advantage of more
than just our outreach programs.
How do you catch them?
Here it is,
3:00 P.M. Wednesday.
There's Orlando.
That's him.
Damn it.
Come on. Come on.
Yes.
So that's what you look like.
I'm gonna run this through Army C.I.D.
If they met in the military
someone in Orlando's old unit
might be able to I.D. him.
No, no, we don't know who's involved
and we don't know how high this goes.
The minute we put this photo out there,
these people are gonna know.
He's gonna disappear,
and we'll never see him again.
We have to do this one on our own.
Beckett, that's impossible.
All we have is a face--
no name, no I.D., no way to find this guy.
Then we will find a way to find him.
I'm not gonna lose this lead.
How are we supposed to investigate
if we can't investigate?
You heard the lady.
We find a way.
Kate!
Don't die on me!
Who hired you to kill her?
Forget it. You'll never touch 'em.
Hey.
I just got off the phone with Esposito.
Our killer had a keychain,
and he matched it to Eastway Car Rentals.
That could be any one of a thousand cars.
I know, it's a needle in a haystack,
but at least it's a haystack,
and they keep most of
their licenses on file.
Kate--
Yeah, he's probably using a fake I.D.
But we should be able to
narrow it down from there.
Kate.
What's wrong?
You, um...
You have to stop.
This investigation, you--you have to stop.
Castle, we already talked about this.
I'm fine. I'm in control.
No, you're not.
They are.
And if you don't stop,
they will kill you, Kate.
What are you talking about?
Before Montgomery went into that hangar,
he sent a package to someone,
someone... he trusted.
It contained information
damaging to the person behind all this.
Montgomery was trying to protect you.
But the package didn't arrive
until after you'd been shot.
Montgomery's friend...
struck a deal with them.
If they left you alone,
that package and the information inside
would never see the light of day.
But they made one condition--
you had to back off.
And that's the reason you're alive, Kate,
because you stopped.
How do you know this?
In order for the deal to work,
someone had to make sure
you weren't pursuing it.
Are you a part of this?
I was just trying to keep you safe.
By lying to me
about the most important thing in my life?
That lie was the only thing
that was protecting you.
Castle, I didn't need protection.
I needed a lead,
and you sat on it for a year.
Now who is this person? How do I find him?
He's a-a voice on the phone.
He's a shadow in a parking garage.
You met with him?
How do you know that he's
not behind my mom's murder?
How do you know that he's not involved?
And how the hell could you do this?
Because I love you.
But you already know that, don't you?
You've known for about a year.
Are you kidding me?
You're actually bringing this up right now,
after you told me that
you just betrayed me?
Kate, listen to me--
Listen to you? Why should I listen to you?
How I am even supposed to
trust anything that you say?
How are you s--
Because of everything we've
been through together!
Four years, I've been right here.
Four years just waiting for
you to just open your eyes,
to see that I'm right here
and that I'm more than a partner.
Every morning, I-I bring
you a cup of coffee
just so I could see a smile on your face
because I think you are the most...
remarkable...
maddening...
challenging...
frustrating person I have ever met.
And I love you, Kate, and if...
that means anything to you,
if you care about me at
all, just don't do this.
If I care about you?
Castle, you cut a deal for my life
like I was some kind of a child.
My life, mine...
You don't get to decide.
You keep going with this,
they're gonna decide.
They're gonna come for you, Kate.
Let them come.
They sent Coonan, and he is dead.
They sent Lockwood, and he is dead.
And I am still here, Castle,
and I am ready.
Ready for what,
to-to die for your cause?
This isn't a murder
investigation anymore, Kate.
They've turned it into a war.
If they want a war, then
I will bring them a war,
straight to their doorsteps.
Well, I guess there's just
nothing I can say, is there?
Okay, um...
Yeah, you're right, Kate,
it's your life.
You can throw it away if you want,
but I'm not gonna stick
around and watch you,
so this is, uh...
over.
I'm done.
Everything okay?
Yeah. Fine. How's your speech coming?
I have watched or read
every graduation address ever written
and compiled all the best
advice into one speech,
and then I read it out loud.
And guess what I sounded like.
Like a pompous ass.
I'm 18 years old. What the hell do I know?
Hey, look, everything you know,
everything you will know is...
is what's true for you.
All I know is, everything's changing.
Everything's going to be different,
and I'm so scared.
Of what?
Moving on.
Write about that.
That feels true.
Where's Castle?
He's off the team.
So what do we got?
Eastway rented 700 cars last Wednesday.
We believe our suspect
is going under the name
Cole Maddox.
He rented out of J.F.K.
It's a Kansas driver's license.
Now we did some digging.
It's a cover I.D.
Did he return the car?
No, but...
Eastway maintains
GPS tracking on all of its equipment,
so we tracked it to the Lower East Side
to a 1-block radius somewhere along here.
All right, you stay on grid.
Let us know if he moves.
Esposito, you're coming with me.
What are you doing?
You want to do this, you do it right.
You put a team on that car and
you bring backup with you.
Ryan, this whole thing started
because of a group of corrupt cops.
How do you know there
aren't more out there?
We're about an inch away
from catching this guy,
and I'm not gonna blow it by
advertising our next move.
With all due respect,
this guy put a bullet in your heart
and then he disappeared into the ether.
You cannot go in there unprepared.
Unprepared?
I've been preparing for
this for the past 13 years.
Hey, Javier...
Man, don't let her do this.
It's too big of a risk.
It's all good, bro.
We got this.
Come on. We don't want
to miss her speech...
or the entire graduation.
I'm almost ready.
Hey, we got him.
The doorman at the residency hotel
across the way I.D.'ed the car.
And the front desk clerk confirms
that Mr. Maddox is here on a 1-month lease.
They've agreed to let us in his room.
Get out of the way.
Clear.
Montgomery's files.
His contact list?
What the hell were they looking for?
Not what. Who.
They grabbed Montgomery's wedding album.
Why?
They're looking for someone that he knew.
Maybe they found him.
We gotta get out of here.
I'm gonna call for backup.
We'll set up in the lobby--
Just tell me who's behind this.
You're wasting your time, detective.
You have no idea what you're up against.
Neither do you.
Actually...
We know exactly who we're up against.
Help!
Oh! Oh, God.
No!
Oh, not like this. Come on.
Come on. No!
Castle.
Beckett!
Castle!
Beckett! Castle, I'm here!
No!
Oh, God. Castle!
Beckett, hang on!
Castle!
Beckett!
Castle?
Withholding evidence,
lying to a superior officer--
What you did dishonors this
city and dishonors the badge.
Not only are you off this investigation,
I'm putting you both on
administrative leave
effective immediately.
Sir--
Don't you "Sir" me.
You don't deserve to wear the uniform.
Now hand over your badges and guns.
Detective Beckett.
Keep it.
I resign.
There's a universal truth
we all have to face...
whether we want to or not.
Everything eventually ends.
As much as I've looked forward to this day,
I've always disliked endings...
The last day of summer...
The final chapter of a great book...
Parting ways with a close friend.
But endings are inevitable.
Javi.
I had to.
Leaves fall.
You close the book.
You say good-bye.
Today is one of those days for us.
Today we say good-bye to
everything that was familiar,
everything that was comfortable.
We're moving on.
But just because we're leaving,
and that hurts...
There are some people
who are so much a part of us
they'll be with us no matter what.
They are our solid ground...
Our North Star,
and the small clear voices in our hearts
that will be with us... always.
No, Alexis, I'll be fine.
I got a thousand cable
channels, I got my Xbox.
You have fun.
I will not worry about you
until lunchtime tomorrow.
I love you, too.
Beckett, what do you want?
You.
I'm so sorry, Castle.
I'm so sorry.
What happened?
He got away, and I didn't care.
I almost died
and all I could think about was you.
I just want you.
Mister...
Smith?
Who are you?
You've been a very hard man to find.
What do you want?
You have some sensitive information
about my employer,
information that you've been using
to protect detective Beckett.
Are you forgetting...
we have a deal?
No. What you had was blackmail.
Now you're gonna tell me where
all that information is,
and after you do,
I'm gonna put Kate Beckett in the ground
once and for all.
Sync by YYeTs
Corrections by honeybunny
www.addic7ed.com
www.tvsubtitles.net